[{"question":"<p><strong>If 45% of the Nigeria naira(N) is equal to 35% of a foreign currency $, the conversion rate of $ to N is $1<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N7\/9","N1 2\/7","N2 2\/9","N2 6\/7"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A headmaster contributes 7% of his income into a fund and his wife contributes 4% of her income. If the husband earns N5,500 per annum and the wife ears N4,000 per annum, find the sum of&nbsp; their annual contributins to the fund.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N1,045","N605","N545","N490"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A Headmaster contributes 7% of his income into a fund and his wife contributes 4% of her income. If the husband earns N5,500 per annum and the wife ears N4,000 per annum, find the sum of their annual contributions to the fund.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N1,045","N605","N545","N490"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The Malthusian theory of population does not concern itself with ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["negative checks to population growth","positive checks to population growth","development and growth of manpower","growth of population in geometric progress"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>A system whereby an employee changes both his occupation and industry is an example of what mobility?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["vertical","horizontal","occupational","geographical"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>What amount of money can be created from a deposit of N300,000 if the current cash ratio is 20%?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N15 million","N1.5 million","N60,000","N600,000"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most liquid asset of a bank is ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["money at call","bank draft","money order","cash"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Where can Nigeria be located on the production possibility curve?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["outside the boundary","on the boundary","inside the boundary","it is indeterminate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economics is that study of human behaviour as it relates to the ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["consumption of goods","production of goods","distribution of goods","efficient allocation of resources"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Opportunity cost is the same as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["social cost","real cost","marginal cost","circulating cost"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a measure of dispersion?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["mean deviation","arithmetic mean","range","variance"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>Long-run production is called...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["returns to scale","economies of scale","large scale production","diminishing returns"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>An output combination below a production possibility boundary indicates that ...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["output is over produced","resources are more than enough for production","resources are maximized","resources are being under-utilized"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>When all factor inputs are reduced by half, the production possibility curve will shift&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["upwards","downwards","inwards","outwards"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The maximum number of shareholders to own a joint stock company is...<\/strong><\/p>","options":["7","2","20","50"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2010"},{"question":"<p><strong>The average sales in a shop for the first 11 weeks of a quater were N86830 per week. The sales for the two remaining weeks of the quarter average N84685 per week. What was the average weekly sales for the quarter?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N85757.50","N85600","N86500","N86830"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The percentage bar graphs may be used in place of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["divided circles","pie charts","dot maps","multiple bar charts"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Those who own and control the means of production in a capitalist society, according to Marxist theory are known as:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["colonialist","proletariat","imperialist","bourgeoise"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The major problem of ECOWAS is lack of:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["ideological homogeneity","a common currency","commitment by members","a common custom union"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Division of labour may be restricted when&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["an ailing economic has improved","producers live in villages","market is small","there is full employment"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>When private consumption expenditure (e) changed from N200m to N250, the MPC was 0.75. Determine the changes in National income level<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N250m","N200m","N400m","N500m"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>If investment is N60, government expenditure N50, consumption N100 + 0.75y, exports N80 and imports N50, what is the equilibrium level of National income<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N860","N760","N960","N660"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>There is overpopulation<\/strong><\/p>","options":["when a country is full of so many people","when there are more people than can make the best use of the available resources","when there are more people than the food available","where there are too many people per kilometer of land"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>An economic problem arises when<\/strong><\/p>","options":["manufactured goods are in short supply","scarcity and choice are involved","money is in short supply","buyers and sellers are few"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>If two commodities are good substitutes for one another e.g. ovaltine and bournvita an increase in the demand for one will reduce the demand for the other. This type of demand is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["composite demand","competitive demand","elastic demand","inelastic demand"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following situation can give rise to economic problems<\/strong><\/p>","options":["unlimited human wants","wants of varying importance","limited means available for satisfying wants","wants used in different ways"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The following are the principles or attributes of a good tax system except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["certainty","convertibility","equity or fairness","economy"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Decreasing returns to scale implies that if the factors of production are doubled output will be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["more than doubled","less than doubled","at equilibrium","unchanged"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The population of Surulere Local Government Area at the beginning of year 2000 was 5 million. The births were 300,000. The deaths were 200,000. In the same year immigrants were 50,000 while emigrants were 20,000 compute the council's population figure at the end of 2000<\/strong><\/p>","options":["36,000","32,000","5,130,000","1,000,000"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Opportunity cost is the term which describes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the initial cost of setting up a business","the cost of one product in terms of the forgone production of others","monetary equivalent of the utility of a commodity","monetary inequivalent of the utility of a commodity"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Decreaing returns to scale implies that if all factors of production are doubled output will be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["more than double","less than double","doubled unchanged","single unchanged"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Rent and interest are rewards to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["labour and capital respectively","land only","capital only","land and capital respectively"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following market structures are imperfect in competition?<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>i Monopoly<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>ii Duopoly<\/strong><\/p>\r\n<p><strong>iii Oligopoly<\/strong><\/p>","options":["i, ii and iii only","i and iii only","i and ii only","ii and iii only"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The profit of the producer can be calculated as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["total cost less total revenue","average revenue less average cost","total revenue less total cost","marginal revenue less marginal cost"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The term \"demand for money\" means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["willingness of people to hold money","desire to borrow money from people","desire of an individual to invest all his money in projects","willingness of people to keep all the resources in assets"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The lender of last resort in the banking system is the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["last resort bank","commercial bank","central bank","mortgage bank"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The three broad categories of production are<\/strong><\/p>","options":["direct, secondary and extractive","primary, tertiary and direct","primary, secondary and tertiary","secondary, primary and indirect"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>As a firm expands, it enjoys some advantages called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["variable proportions","diminishing marginal returns","internal economies of scale","decreasing returns to scale"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>External economies refer to the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cost-saving advantages a firm enjoys by being close to other firms in the same industry","disadvantages to a firm that is close to other firms","economies of large scale","economies of small scale"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Tariff can be defined as a compulsory levy on&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["goods that are produced and consumed locally","imports and export","foreign exchange earning","difference between exports and imports"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The practice of selling goods overseas that is often below the cost of production is known as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Retailing","Dumping","Internal trade","Advertising"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>The theory of consumer behaviour is based on all the following assumptions except that the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["consumer is assumed irrational","consumer taste remains constant","consumer has budget constraint","consumer aims at maximizing his utility"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>30 apple sellers made an average gain of N27.00 a day. If twelve of them were girls whose average gain&nbsp; a day was N18.00, what was the average gain of the boys per day?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N29.00","N33.00","N21.00","N9.00"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>An economic analysis aimed at explaining what a phenomenon should be comes under the&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["positive approach","social approach","normative approach","logical approach"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The problem of how goods shall be produced in a society implies choices between<\/strong><\/p>","options":["necessities and luxuries","food and cash crops","capital and consumer goods","labour and capital intensive methods"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The prices of goods and services in a capitalist economy is determined by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the consumers","the producers","the consumers and producers","the forces of demand and supply"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a measure of central tendency?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["median","graph","percentage","variance"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>At the point where total utility begins to decline, MU is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["negative","decreasing","zero","increasing"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand for petrol at N65.00 per litre was 330,000 litres per day but when the price rose to N75.00 per litre, the quantity demanded dropped to 220,000 litres. What is the coefficient of the price elasticity of demand?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.17","2.27","0.17","2.36"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A person that retains his skill but moves to a different industry is involved in&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["vertical mobility","horizontal mobility","geographical mobility","occupational mobility"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the average cost and average revenue of a product are N80.00 and N96.00 respectively and 240 units were produced, what is the profit made?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N3,840.00","N16.00","N38.40","N38,400.00"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>When a dealer sells a bicycle for N81,000.00, he makes a profit of 8%. How much did he buy the bicycle?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N73,000.00","N74,520.00","N75,000.00","N75,520.00"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>An economy where prices are determined by the market of demand and supply is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["deregulated economy","command economy","centrally planned economy","regulated economy"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A bar graph where a simple bar carries more than one information in a given period is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["simple bar graph","multiple bar graph","histogram","compound bar graph"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most commonly used of the measures of central tendency is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["mode","median","mean","median and mode"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The rate at which the Central Bank rediscounts bills to commercial banks is called&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["interest rate","bank rate","discount rate","turnover"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not a fixed cost?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["salaries","cost of machines","power","rent"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Agriculture is important to the West African economy because it is the source of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["industrial input","irrigation","equipment supply","technology progress"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Farmers often find it difficult to obtain loans from banks for agricultural projects because they<\/strong><\/p>","options":["lack skills","lack entrepreneurial ability","lack government support","lack collaterals"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Monopolistic competition is a market structure<\/strong><\/p>","options":["characterized by features both of monopoly and perfect competition","characterized by long-running abnormal profits","having features of monopoly but not perfect competition","having features of perfect competition but not monopoly"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The last link in distributive trade is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["consumer","retailer","middleman","producer"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The movement of people from one place to another in order to settle there temporarily or permanently is known as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["migration","emigration","immigration","net migration"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Subsidiary firms are firms&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["that render services to bigger ones","that are formed by localization","formed with government subsidy","formed by merging"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The introduction of machines into work place is likely to cause<\/strong><\/p>","options":["cyclical umemployment","structural unemployment","frictional unemployment","seasonal unemployment"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The downward slope of the production possibility curve shows that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["more of both commodities can be produced without reallocation","the economy is dwindling","all nations are producing at full capacity","there is opportunity cost of production more of one commodity"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the MPC is given 0.8, the level of investment which is required to raise income by N6,000 will be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N1,800","N4,800","N1,200","N30,000"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following could be used to measure efficiency of labour?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["supply of labour","price level","input-output level","labour turnover"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The equilibrium price of a bag is N12, if for some reasons the price rises to N15, there will be<\/strong><\/p>","options":["price legislation","excess demand","excess supply","shortage in the market"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>If the price of a commodity rises from N2.00 to N2.50 and its supply increases from 100 to 120, then the coefficient of elasticity of supply is?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.25","0.8","2.5","1.25"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The cross of elasticity of demand for complementary goods is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["normal","positive","negative","constant"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>An undergraduate has one thousand naira only as his pocket money and desires to buy a pair of shoes and a book. If the two items cost one thousand naira each, what should he do?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["buy the book and forgo a pair of shoes","buy a pair of shoe and forgo the book","buy either of the two","buy the more pressing item"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>One advantage of socialist economy is that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["consumer exploration is minimal","private enterprises are more productive","goods are distributed on the basis of economic power","government participation in economic activity minimal"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following countries is not a member of the Organisation of Petroleum Exporting Countries(OPEC)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Mexico","Nigeria","Saudi Arabia","Venezuela"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most important characteristics of a population that enhances rapid economic development is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["total size","age structure","level of education","size of the population"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is a commercial service?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["transporting","garri processing","oil drilling","lumbering"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following allows production to take place ahead of demand?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["transportation","wholesaling","exporting","warehousing"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following correctly describes the basis for international trade?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["terms of trade","absolute cost advantage","comparative cost advantage","division of labour"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Who defined Economics as the study of mankind in the ordianry business of life?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Alfred Marshal","David Richards","Adam Smith","Professor Lionel Robbins"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economics is called a social science because it is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["a branch of social studies","a study of the ways man devices to study his unlimited wants for limited resources","a dismal science in the Malthusian sense","the study of human wants by means of scientific methods and observation"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic good is one which<\/strong><\/p>","options":["is economically good","is scarce","yields utility and commands a price","is efficiently produced"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a country has a large labour force, it is beneficial for it to adopt a&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["capital intensive method of production","labour intensive method of production","large intensive method of production","land\/labour intensive method of production"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Production can be defined as<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the creation of something","the rendering of services by professionals","the manufacturing of goods","the creation of utility"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The demand for a factor of production is a&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["derived demand","composite demand","competitive demand","joint demand"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>If AC = Average cost of production, FC = Fixed cost of production, VC = Variable cost of production and TC = Total cost of production, then VC is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["TC\/FC","FC = AC","TC + FC","TC - FC"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Price can be defined as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["rate of exchange","cost of production","medium of exchange","standard of living"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Let Q = Total output of yam (in kilogram), AC = Average cost of production, TVC = Total Variable&nbsp;cost of production, TFC = Total fixed&nbsp;cost of production, TC = Total&nbsp;cost of production then average cost can be defined in symbols as:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["AC = TFC\/Q","AC = TC + TVC","AC = TC X Q","AC = TVC\/Q"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>An inferior good is one<\/strong><\/p>","options":["whose quality is low","which is consumed by the poor","whose demand rises as income falls","whose demand rises as inferiority rises"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>The main handicap of sole proprietorship is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["inadequate capital","lack of technical know how","high profit margin","low profit margin"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following does not carry fixed rate of dividend?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["participatory preference shares","cumulative preference shares","ordinary shares","preference shares"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>An important characteristics of money which makes it possible for a person to provide for old age is known as&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["store of value","medium of exchange","old age characteristics","old school money"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Farmers income may fall if they produce more cash crops for export because<\/strong><\/p>","options":["foreign demand is inelastic","foreign demand is elastic","domestic currency depreciates","domestic currency appreciates"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Deficit financing means<\/strong><\/p>","options":["deficits in financing a budget","receiving grants from I.M.F","inadequate supply of money in the economy","borrowing to finance a budget"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>What do you understand by \"Terms of Trade?\"<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the direction of foreign trade","the quality of imports","the rate at which exports exchange for raw imports","the rate at which exports exchange for raw materials"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Economic growth specifically refers to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["increase in the population of a country","increase in the mineral oil of the country","sustained increase in the output of goods and services","growth in the economic sector"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>If C stands for total expenditure on consumption and Y stands for total income, then average propensity to consume<\/strong><\/p>","options":["APC = C\/Y","APC = Y\/C","APC = Y - C","APC = Y + C"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2005"},{"question":"<p><strong>Under the ECOWAS agreement, a Nigerian can enter and stay in Ivory Coast without a visa for<\/strong><\/p>","options":["30 days","60 days","90 days","120 days"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2005"}]